All right, בוקר טוב. boker tov.
Today's דף daf is officially מ"א, mem aleph, we're 41, we're a
little bit behind. We pick up at the bottom of מ' עמוד
ב'. mem amud beis. We just had done the משנה, mishnah, we're
in the גמרא gemara right after the משנה. mishnah. We just had
done the משנה mishnah that said moved on to the other payments
by the case of rape and we have בושת boshes and פגם
pegam as well as צער, tzaar, although interestingly צער tzaar is not
going to be addressed. And by בושת boshes it goes according to
the degree of embarrassment based on the person doing the embarrassment and
the person embarrassed. And the פגם pegam goes by the slave market
and it repeated the idea that the קנס, knas, the 50 שקל
shekel was fixed for everyone. So the גמרא gemara right afterwards at
the very bottom of מ' עמוד א', mem amud aleph, ואימא ve-eima
says the גמרא gemara חמישים זוזי אמר רחמנא מכל מילי. chamishim zuzi
amar rachmana mi-kol milei. How do you know that you pay these
additional payments that you normally pay for assault, how do you know
you pay it in addition to the 50 שקל? shekel? Maybe the
50 שקל shekel covers all of that? אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi
Zeira, אמרו amru because people will say, no, just look at it
logically.
בת מלכים חמישים בת הדיוטות חמישים? Bas melachim chamishim, bas hedyotos chamishim?
If this guy basically has sex with, but
obviously talking about rape, it's true that this also does apply to
the case of seduction, but anyway, if he rapes a princess, he
pays 50, the daughter of a king, and if he rapes somebody
from a high status, that's what he pays and if he rapes
somebody a layperson, daughter of a layperson, he pays 50? Meaning it's
crazy that there should be just one payment and it wouldn't make
a difference based on the actual amount of shame and injury and
so on that was done. There would be no fairness to it.
אמר ליה אביי, Amar leh Abaye, so אביי Abaye said back to
this, אי הכי i hachi if that's true, גבי עבד נמי. gabei
eved nami. So how about another place where the תורה Torah sets
a fixed amount and there we don't look at differences? It says
אמרו לו amru lo when an ox gores a slave, he pays
30 שקל. shekel. So אמרו, amru, will people say, עבד נוקב מרגליות
שלושים? eved nokeiv margoliyos sheloshim? If you have a slave that's able
to basically make holes in pearls, you have a slave that could
earn a thousand dollars an hour and an ox gored it and
all you do is pay 30 שקל? shekel? עבד עושה מעשה מחט,
Eved oseh maaseh machat,
and you have another slave that all he can do is he's
a tailor, makes two dollars an hour and also שלושים, sheloshim, 30
שקל? shekel? So there's unfairness there too, but there are times the
תורה Torah sets a fixed amount, so here too maybe the תורה
Torah sets a fixed amount. אלא אמר רבי זירא, Ella amar Rabbi
Zeira, so רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira says consider the following contrast, not
about the question about social standing but the following difference. אילו בא
עליה שניים, Elu ba aleha shenayim, if two people rape her, אחד
כדרכה ואחד שלא כדרכה. echad ke-darkah ve-echad she-lo ke-darkah. The first one
not in the natural way, meaning anal sex, and the next one
natural, or as תוספות Tosafos points out the second
one, first one is natural.
The language here is that way but it means the order I
said.
Because of the point the גמרא's gemara making and תוספות Tosafos says
that explicitly as I'll say. The point being because we want the
second one to be paying 50 שקל shekel as well. So if
the first one raped her through vaginal intercourse then she would no
longer be a virgin and then the second one wouldn't pay. But
interestingly, for the purposes of נערה בתולה na'arah besulah for the 50
שקל, shekel, if she actually has had sex and it's anal sex
and it did not rupture the hymen, didn't have the potential of
rupturing the hymen, she is still considered a virgin for the הלכה
halacha of the 50 שקל. shekel. So therefore, in this scenario where
the first one raped her שלא כדרכה she-lo ke-darkah anally and the
second one, it really doesn't matter which way, but that's why the
second one is also paying 50 שקל. shekel. The point is you
have these two people for the same, raping the same woman paying
50 שקל. shekel. So will they say, יאמרו yomru will people say,
בא על שלמה חמישים בא על פגומה חמישים? ba al sheleimah chamishim,
ba al pegumah chamishim? That the guy who raped the woman that
was a full woman, as it were, a woman who had never
had sex, pays 50, and the next guy also pays 50? That
would be crazy, that wouldn't be logical. The funny thing of course
is here, besides of course the horrific scenario that the גמרא's gemara
describing, but the strange thing is why is that better than the
earlier question? I mean basically it's just
saying woman of high status, it was a greater injury this and
that. Here it's not so clear why there should be such a
difference based on whether this woman had sex before even if she
wasn't or was raped before even if she wasn't, and therefore
no longer was a virgin,
that that should somehow obviously mean that the amount of the fine
is going to be less.
I
understand the different framing, the primary difference of the framing is not
that from our sense that there's a logic it should be less
money, but it seems to be from our perspective I think if
anything the first question was a much better one, but it's that
this has to do with the physical state of her body. So
maybe the גמרא gemara assumes that since her physical state of her
body is different that therefore it's more obvious that there should be...
to be a difference in terms of payment. So אמר ליה אביי,
amar lei Abaye, so Abaye said back to this, אי הכי גבי
עבד נמי, ee hachi gabi eved nami, so so what? Make the
same argument by the slave when the ox gores it. יאמר עבד
בריא שלושים עבד מוכה שחין שלושים, yomar eved bari shloshim eved mukeh
shchin shloshim, let's say you have nice healthy, you know, physically fit
עבד, eved, and you have another one that's, you know, that's that's
diseased and you know and and whatever right right right right's weak
and diseased and covered with boils and whatever, so that also's the
same amount. So basically by the עבד eved you have an example
that regardless of the person's social standing
or you know, financial- you know ability to you know, earning potential
or physical state, it's going to be the same amount for one
עבד eved and the next. So therefore, if it says 50 שקל
shekel by this case of rape, maybe it's the same regardless of
the woman's status. How do you know that there are differences beyond
the קנס knas based on, you know, בושת ופגם? boshet u'pgam? Maybe
it's the 50 covers everything and no difference based on the person.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so that's the question. So the גמרא
Gemara says אלא אמר אביי, ela amar Abaye, so Abaye says here,
we get it from a פסוק. pasuk. We don't get it from
a purely logical argument, we get it from a פסוק. pasuk. אלא
אמר אביי, ela amar Abaye, אמר קרא amar kra says תחת אשר
ענה tachat asher ina that you should pay the 50 שקל shekel
in exchange for that he has oppressed, you know, raped this woman.
הני תחת אשר ענה, hani tachat asher ina, the 50 שקל shekel
is for the act of rape, for the act of intercourse, forceful
intercourse. מכלל דאיכא בושת ופגם, miklal de'ika boshet u'pgam, there are other
payments that are for other things, not just for the act of
forceful intercourse itself but for the associated embarrassment and devaluing of the
woman and so on. רבא אמר אמר קרא, Rava amar amar kra,
Rava learns from another verse. The verse says ונתן האיש השוכב עמה
לאבי הנערה חמישים כסף, v'natan ha'ish hashocheiv ima l'avi hana'ara chamishim kasef,
the man who sleeps with her shall pay to the father 50
כסף. kesef. So it says it combines sleeping with her and the
payment. So הנאת שכיבה חמישים, hana'at shchiva chamishim, the payment for the
pleasure of
sex is 50. מכלל דאיכא בושת ופגם miklal de'ika boshet u'pgam to
tell you that there is other payments, the payments of embarrassment and
damages. So basically they just say that the 50 in the תורה
Torah is for the act of intercourse and not for the associated
other types of injuries that occur or damage that occurs. Of course,
again, it's just from our perspective, the way of describing this as
הנאת שכיבה, hana'at shchiva, the pleasure of the act of sex, I
mean maybe from the rapist's perspective, but but yes, I understand. Still,
though, it's a little troubling. Anyway, the 50 שקל shekel is for
the act of sex per se and for the act of rape
per se but not for the associated injuries and damages and so
on. Now the גמרא Gemara moves on—so that's how we know the
idea that there's these other payments as well. So now the גמרא
Gemara goes on with another question. ואימא לדידה, ve'eima l'dida, how do
you know, because the תורה Torah says the 50 שקל shekel goes
to the father? It doesn't say now that you've sort of inferred
that there's these other payments, תורה Torah doesn't say where that goes.
Maybe the בושת ופגם boshet u'pgam go to the woman? Now the
obvious answer to this that תוספות Tosafot already points out is, is
that, and the גמרא's Gemara's going to more or less point out
later, is that you know it can't go to the woman because
if it goes to the woman then in the case of פיתוי,
pitui, in the case of seduction, there would be no payment. Because
if fundamentally the woman deserves it, then when she's doing it consensually,
there would be no payment. Maybe there'd be the 50 שקל shekel
because that's the father, but but there would be no payment to
her for the פיתוי pitui and
the בושת ופגם, boshet u'pgam, she's consenting. The fact that we have
those payments in the case of פיתוי, pitui, in the case of
seduction, proves that they are the father's payments. And therefore even if
the girl consents, the father didn't consent, and therefore those payments are
still going to take place. So that's how we know that the
משנה Mishna assumes that that goes straight to the father. But what
we want to know is, how do we learn it from the
פסוק? pasuk? Right? Once we're asserting now that there's these other payments
implicit in the פסוק, pasuk, or the פסוק pasuk is only talking
about one aspect but there would naturally be these other payments because
it's an act of injury, what's our basis based on the verse
to say that that goes to the father? Maybe it should go
to her. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ואימא לדידה, ve'eima l'dida, maybe it goes to her. אמר קרא, amar
kra, the verse says בנעוריה בית אביה, binureha beit aviha, a verse
by the annulment of vows, it says that the father annuls the
vows when she is in her youth in the father's house. So
from there we try to make a general principle that it's not
just about annulling vows.
כל שבח נעורים לאביה, kol shevach neurim l'aviha, all benefits that come
from her youth go to the father. So any type of money
or power or control vis-a-vis her is her father's while she's still
a נערה. na'ara. So therefore these are damages, these would go to
the father, not just the 50 שקל. shekel. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא הא דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, ela ha de'amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav, so that what Rav Yehuda said in the name
of Rav, מניין שמעשה בת לאביה, minayin she'maaseh bat l'aviha, how do
you know that if a daughter earns money while she's still
a קטנה ktana or a
נערה, na'ara, how do you know it
goes to the
father? שנאמר, shene'emar, as
it is said... He is actually the master
then.
He is the master
before he sells her to another man, right? Before he sells her
to another man. So there you see that her earnings go to
the father. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says if that, so that's
a pretty good, you know, learning derivation from that verse. But the
גמרא Gemara says, but on you, but according to you, תפוק ליה
מבין נעוריה בבית אביה. tapuq leh mi-bein neureiha be-veit aviha. If you
try to say that this verse by vows, annulling vows, is a
general, teaches you a general rule that the father has total control
and rights to his daughter. But that's not true, because then we
wouldn't have needed to learn that his rights to her earnings from
this other verse of selling her as a slave. The fact that
we learn that he has rights to her earnings from this verse
of selling her as a slave shows that there's not a big
general umbrella rule that he gets all of the benefits that derive
from her. And why is that? Why don't we learn it from
the verse בין נעוריה בבית אביה? bein neureiha be-veit aviha? So the
גמרא Gemara says אלא ההוא בהפרת נדרים הוא דכתיב. ela hahu behafarat
nedarim hu deketiv.
That verse of in her youth in her father's house is specifically
about his right to annul her vows. וכי תימא נילף מיניה, ve-chi
teima nilaf mineih, okay, but let's use that as a paradigm and
apply, if he can annul her vows, maybe he has all rights
to her. No, ממונא מאיסורא לא ילפינן. mamona meisura lo yalpinan. Rights
about, you know, איסור, issur, about things like vows, about obligations and
transgressions, do not necessarily translate into things that are true about monetary
rights. So we don't know from there. So from the first בין
נעוריה בבית אביה, bein neureiha be-veit aviha, you only know he has
the right to annul the vows. From the verse of וכי ימכור
איש את בתו לאמה, vechi yimkor ish et bito leamah, that he
can sell her as a slave, you know he has the rights
to the earnings. But what you don't know is that he has
the rights that derive from injury done to her person. And as
תוספות Tosafot points out, you know, that's a little bit different than
just her earnings. It's one thing to say monetary purposes, she earns
money, the father gets it, fine, you go to a work, you
earn money. But an injury actually done to your person, maybe that's
something that the תורה Torah would say that, you know, you deserve
to get paid for that directly, not the father. So we don't
know it from either of these two verses. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, וכי תימא נילף מקנסא, ve-chi teima nilaf mi-qenasa,
and let's learn out from the fact that okay, the father gets
the fifty shekel. No, ממונא מקנסא לא ילפינן. mamona mi-qenasa lo yalpinan.
קנס, qenas, a fine, is always seen as an exception. So even
though he gets the, the father gets the fifty shekel, that doesn't
mean he gets the monetary payment that are payments for personal injury.
So we don't know, so we know he gets the fine, we
know he gets her earnings, we know he is allowed to annul
the vows. But how do we know he gets the payments for
personal injury? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מסתברא דאביה הוי. ela
mistavra deaviha havei.
No, it actually, here's how come we can assume that the father
gets those. ואי בעית מוסרה למנוול ולמוכת שחין, ve-i bayit mosrah le-menuval
u-le-mukeh shechin, because he actually does have power over these things as
well. How does he have the power? He can decide who to
marry her off to. So the problem is now, why are there
these other payments? There's these other payments for בושת, boshet,
the embarrassment,
and
for פגם. pegam. The פגם pegam is that she's no longer a
virgin. So the father can control that. He can marry her off,
and that'll mean that she'll become no longer a virgin. So any
payment that comes as a result of her no longer being a
virgin is something he had control over. How about the issue of
shame? Well, the father can marry her off to a disgusting person
which will bring her a lot of shame. So since he has
control over her shame, therefore he gets paid for it. Now, of
course, what's funny about that is that again, not distinguishing between the
shame about being married to somebody of, let's say, a lowly status
as opposed to the shame of being raped, number one. Okay, number
two is is that there's also the whole question that I, that
we've been asking is about shame, who is shamed? Is it the
girl who's shamed? So then how is there a payment when she
does it consensually? Are we saying she's shamed even if she's willing
to be shamed? It seems like we're saying that because it doesn't
seem like we're talking about the shame of the father, because then
it would be more obvious. If it was about the shame of
the father, then he got that shame and it should be paid
for it directly. Okay, but we presumably don't say that. We say
shame is only paid to the person who's injured. So it's only
paid to the girl. So that just leads to the funny example
that even in the case of consensual sex, of seduction, we still
say that there's a payment of בושת boshet that she is considered
to have been shamed even though she agreed to it willingly. That's
just one interesting point. So she's the one who is shamed, she's
the one who becomes not a virgin, the father can bring similar
statuses on her, not virgin, yes, not the exact same type of
shame, and therefore we say he's in control of that and therefore
he gets the payment. The other thing, however, that's not addressing is
that by the case of rape, there's also a payment. of צער,
Tza'ar, of suffering, and you know, again, the father can maybe marry
her off to a man and she'll have some suffering when she
has that first act of sex, but that gets us back to
the early גמרא Gemara that basically was, you know, was having a
hard time understanding why there's more pain and suffering by rape than
by consensual sex, which was obviously a challenging, a difficult גמרא. Gemara.
But nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara conceded that there was, so it's still
not exactly clear why he gets the payment of צער, Tza'ar, right?
He doesn't presumably marry her off in order to be raped by
her husband. So anyway, but the גמרא Gemara sort of says based
on the ideas that he has all of this complete control over
her, it makes sense to say that once we say she does
get these payments, that the payments do go to the father. One
minute, let's just finish up to the משנה. Mishnah. פגם, Pegam, אונס,
Ones, כאילו היא שפחה נמכרת, ke'ilu hi shifcha nimkeret, when you figure
out the damages, you determine it based as if she was a
woman being sold like you normally determine any damages, based on the
slave market. So the גמרא Gemara says, היכי שמינין לה? Heichi shammenan
lah? How do we evaluate her? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar
Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, אומדין, omdim, we estimate כמה אדם רוצה ליתן
בין שפחה בתולה לשפחה בעולה לשמשו. kamma adam rotze liten bein shifcha
betula leshifcha be'ula lishamesho. How much would a person pay for a
virgin maid servant as opposed to one who has had sex in
order to, you know, attend to him, to go ahead and like
I don't know, be a house slave. So the גמרא Gemara says,
one minute, שפחה בעולה לשמשו מאי נפקא ליה מיניה? Shifcha be'ula lishamesho
mai nafka leh minei? So the גמרא Gemara says, שפחה בעולה לשמשו
מאי נפקא ליה
מיניה?
Shifcha be'ula lishamesho mai nafka
leh minei?
So what difference does it make? If all this person is doing
is, I don't know, she's cooking in the kitchen, what does he
care whether she's a virgin or not? אלא, Ella, בין שפחה בעולה
לשפחה שאינה בעולה להשיאה לעבדו. bein shifcha be'ula leshifcha she'eina be'ula lehasi'ah
le'avdo.
No, he wants to buy this maid servant in order to marry
her off to his slave, and therefore his slave cares whether she's
a virgin or not. So therefore he'll pay a higher price for
a virgin. So the גמרא Gemara says, ולעבדו מאי נפקא ליה מיניה?
Ule'avdo mai nafka leh minei? So what does he care whether his
slave wants, you know, would rather, you know, marry a virgin or
not? All the master cares about is making babies. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, בעבד שיש לו לרבו קורת רוח הימנו, be'eved sheyesh
lo larabbo korat ruach himenu, it's a slave that the master like
likes and therefore he wants to do the slave a favor. So
he wants to do the slave a favor, he'll buy the slave
a woman who's a virgin as opposed to a slave woman who's
not a virgin. So once again we get this whole commodification of
the woman. Now of course you get this by even by personal
injury as well. You ask about like a man's arm is broken.
How much would you pay in the slave market for a person
with an arm and without an arm? And whatever, the תורה Torah
has to and הלכה Halacha has to determine how to the dollar
value for personal injury, it does it based on the slave market
because that's the only model that it has of assigning a dollar
value to a person.
Now for us it seems very besides, you know, that it's objectifying,
which I mean slavery was totally objectifying to human beings and now
but now that's now being applied to us.
But in addition of course the question is like how is that
at all fair? Like I mean, you know, does that at all
approximate? I mean there are other payments, you know, pain and suffering
and so on but it really is, you know, it does not
seem like it would at all right at all approximate, you know,
in type of a dollar amount that somebody might feel would be
actually fair compensation. But that's the reality of this payment of the
פגם. Pegam. Now תוספות Tosafot asks a question and תוספות Tosafot says
one minute, if you like it's one thing to say somebody broke,
you know, somebody's arm was broken and so when you pay for
the difference about a slave with an arm and without an arm
essentially you're also paying for like the loss of earnings because if
a slave with an arm could let's say make, you know, could
earn you a hundred thousand dollars a year because I don't know
he was a quarterback for a football team or something and slave
without an arm could only earn twenty thousand dollars a year and
you multiply that by the years of productive labor of the slave
and that would factor into the different price of the slave. So
to some degree it would approximate the actual loss in terms of
at least the loss of earnings. Okay but תוספות Tosafot says in
this issue of a woman becoming a non-virgin the loss to the
person if you think about it let's say this person is of
a very high social standing and she was a virgin or whatever
so she would have gotten herself a husband of a very high
social standing as well. Now this is a woman who has who
is not a virgin, has been raped, she won't be able like
to maybe, you know, marry somebody of an upper class. That's a
huge loss. It's not just a loss about how much difference it
would make to marry a type of a woman, you know, who
was a virgin versus non-virgin to your slave, right? That's maybe worth
I don't know a hundred dollars to your slave or a thousand
dollars or whatever but it's not necessarily does not reflect the loss
of to the person which, you know, which might at least differ
based on other factors as well. So if you take a look
at תוספות, Tosafot, כמה אדם רוצה ליתן להשיאה לעבדו, Kamma adam rotze
liten lehasi'ah le'avdo, תוספות Tosafot says תימה דמאי שומא היא זו וכי
אשה חשובה ממשפחה גדולה אינה נפסדת בפגמה אלא שוה שפחה הנישאת לעבד?
Teimah demai shuma hi zo
vechi isha chashuva mimishpacha gedola einah nifsedet bepigma ella shaveh shifcha hanisset
le'eved?
Is that the only difference? Meaning even if acknowledging that there's already
a bizarre equation to the slave market but at least the slave
market equation by other things takes into account other differences like was
this person a high earner or not a high earner. That would
be reflected in the slave market price, but with this woman and
what her virginity meant to her is not reflected in the slave
market price. So the גמרא Gemara says: ויש לומר דכל אשה שמין
לפי מה שהיא בענין זה כמה אדם רוצה ליתן בין בתולה לבעולה
להשיא לעבדו אשה כזאת הנפגמת. veyesh lomar dechol isha shamin lefi ma
shehi beinyan ze kama adam rotze litein bein betula lebeula lehashi leavdo
isha kazot hanifgemet.
Okay, so תוספות Tosafot says, תוספות Tosafot basically says, well, no, it
would be the difference of if you wanted to buy in the
slave market a woman of very high social standing, I don't know
what she would be doing being sold in the slave market, you
know, and how much would that difference be between בתולה betula and
בעולה? beula?
For your עבד eved though.
But it would still be right for your עבד. eved. I understand.
So it's, but anyway at least he puts the problem on the
table. Rabbi Dov, you had a question before?
Yeah, a couple of things. First of all, I don't understand really
why the תלמוד Talmud has to get involved with needing a different
פסוק pasuk as in the case when the father sells the daughter,
you
would think that he has transferred his
ריבונות ribonut from himself to the new master. You would need a
פסוק pasuk to say, no, that's not the case. That's not exactly
what the תלמוד Talmud does.
Huh? I don't understand.
Wait a minute, I have a daughter, I sell her, she now
has a new master. Right. So you would think that I have
given up my masterhood over my daughter. You have. So you need
a פסוק pasuk to say, yeah, no, that's not the case.
What do you mean it's not the case? I don't understand what
you're saying. The פסוק pasuk told you that after you sold her,
when you sold her, you don't get her earnings. When it says
מעשה בת לאביה, maase bat leaviha, it means how do you know
you're entitled to her earnings when you haven't sold? From the fact
that you can sell her and give her earnings over to somebody
else shows you that when you haven't sold her, you're entitled to
her earnings. It's
not telling you you're entitled to earnings after selling her, you're not.
The whole purpose you're selling her is that somebody else gets her
earnings.
Right, so here there's a they quote a פסוק pasuk that corrects
for that, that even after you sell her, the father still retains...
No, that's not what the גמרא Gemara is saying. You misunderstood the
גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara is saying that because that when the
father sells her, the master gets her earnings. From this we learn
that when she isn't sold, the father gets her earnings. Not that
he gets earnings after selling her. No, the whole point of selling
her was that the other master gets her earnings. Yes.
This slave market that we're talking about, is it a Jewish slave
market or non-Jewish slave market?
Yeah, I mean a Jew what do you mean? I mean Jews
could be the buyers, but the slaves being sold are the non
are non-Jews.
Oh, are non-Jews, right? It's not because the Jewish slave is totally
different.
Right, because here the whole point is to assign a dollar value
to a human being or to different values of human beings and
therefore it would only be the non-Jewish slave market where the whole
person is being sold, like the whole dollar value is assigned to
the person, whereas the Jewish slave market you're only buying the labor
for a certain number of years. Okay, it's very yeah, I mean
it's it's a very disturbing map. I mean the slave slave market
in general is deeply disturbing. Now we're just applying it to us.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says moving on. Okay, כל מקום
שיש מכר, kol makom sheyesh mecher, we got to keep moving, we're
way behind. כל מקום שיש מכר אין קנס וכל מקום שיש קנס
אין מכר.
kol makom sheyesh mecher
ein kenas vechol makom sheyesh kenas ein mecher.
So this is the position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that we
quoted before. Where there is sale, meaning while she's while she's a
קטנה, ketana, because the father can only sell her, he can marry
her as a נערה, naara, but he can only sell her as
a קטנה. ketana. So when he can when there is sale up
to the age of 12, then there's no קנס. kenas. קנס kenas
only begins at the at the age of 12 when she's a
נערה. naara. וכל מקום שיש קנס, vechol makom sheyesh kenas, when there's
קנס, kenas, when she's a נערה, naara, אין מכר, ein mecher, he
can't sell her. Again, as a נערה naara she could still be
married off by the father but could not be sold as a
slave. Okay. קטנה יש לה מכר ואין לה קנס נערה יש לה
קנס ואין לה מכר, ketana yesh la mecher veein la kenas naara
yesh la kenas veein la mecher, just spells it out. An underage
girl, a קטנה, ketana, minor, can be sold but not there's no
קנס, kenas, and a נערה, naara, a girl in her youth, whatever,
from 12 to 12 and a half, can there is קנס, kenas,
she can't be sold as a slave. הבוגרת, habogeret, once she is
mature, 12 and a half, a whole ripe age of 12 and
a half, אין לה לא מכר ולא קנס, ein la lo mecher
velo kenas, cannot be sold nor is there a קנס. kenas. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב זו דברי רבי מאיר. amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav zu divrei Rabbi Meir. These are the words of רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, but the sages say, יש לה
קנס במקום מכר. yesh la kenas bemakom mecher. That קנס kenas and
מכר mecher can overlap. That there is קנס kenas even when she's
a קטנה. ketana. דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, קטנה
מבת יום אחד ועד שתביא שתי שערות, ketana mibat yom echad vead
shetavi shetei searot, a קטנה ketana from day
one until she has two pubic hairs, until she's a נערה, naara,
יש לה מכר ואין לה קנס, yesh la mecher veein la kenas,
can be sold but there's no קנס. kenas. No קנס kenas for
קטנה. ketana. משתביא שתי שערות, mishetavi shetei searot, once she has the
two pubic hairs, עד שתבגר, ad shetivager, until she becomes mature, יש
לה קנס ואין לה מכר, yesh la kenas veein la mecher, then
she's a נערה naara and there's a קנס kenas but there's no
sale. דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir,
that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. שהיה רבי מאיר אומר, shehaya
Rabbi Meir omer, because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir used to say, כל
מקום שיש מכר אין קנס וכל מקום שיש קנס אין מכר. kol
makom sheyesh mecher ein kenas vechol makom sheyesh kenas ein mecher. When
there's one, there's not the other. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, and the
sages say, קטנה מבת שלוש שנים ויום אחד ועד שתבגר, ketana mibat
shalosh shanim veyom echad vead shetivager, from three years from one from
one day to three years there's only מכר, mecher, there's no קנס
kenas because it's not considered an act of sex. From three years
until she becomes a בוגרת bogeret through her Bat Mitzvah, through six
months later until she becomes a בוגרת, bogeret, so starting at those
three years once it's an act of sex and she's a and
she's even though she's a קטנה, ketana, מבת שלוש שנים ויום אחד
ועד שתבגר יש לה קנס, mibat shalosh shanim veyom echad vead shetivager
yesh la kenas, she has קנס. kenas. So there's קנס kenas even
for קטנה. ketana. So the גמרא Gemara says, קנס אין מכר לא?
kenas in mecher lo? What, only קנס? kenas? So the גמרא Gemara
says, no, אימא אף קנס במקום מכר. eima af kenas bemakom mecher.
No, clearly, meaning sale goes from birth till twelve. קנס knas is—can
even exist at times when there are sale, קנס knas is even
when she’s a קטנה Ketana from three years and one day all
the way until she’s a בוגרת. Bogeret.
Okay, so this was put a bit more clearly in the... fine.
אמר
רב
חסדא: Amar Rav Chisda: מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר? mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Meir?
What’s the reason of Rabbi Meir? אמר קרא: Amar kra: ולו תהיה
לאשה. v’lo tiyeh l’ishah. It says by the case by a rape:
to him she shall be for a wife. דמהוה עצמה קא משתעי.
d’mehavya atzmah ka mishta’ei.
It’s talking about a woman that can marry herself. Although the father
can marry off the daughter against her will since she’s a נערה,
Na'arah, the woman herself can also accept the כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin.
So she can be part of the process of marrying herself as
a נערה. Na'arah. So since it uses the verb in reference to
her, ולו תהיה לאשה, v’lo tiyeh l’ishah, to him she should be,
it doesn't say to him the father should marry her off, it
seems that we're talking about a נערה. Na'arah. אוקיי, Okay, I mean
the תורה Torah already says נערה, Na'arah, but the way we know
to say only נערה, Na'arah, not קטנה, Ketana, is the repetition here
of this verse which indicates that she is—that she is already halachically
an adult. ורבנן, V’Rabbanan, and the rabbis, what would the rabbis say
back? אמר ריש לקיש: Amar Reish Lakish: אמר קרא, amar kra, the
verse says נערה, Na'arah, here it should be—here it should appear in
the גמרא Gemara without the ה. hei. What does Rabbi Meir learn
from that ולו תהיה לאשה? v'lo tiyeh l'ishah? That she’s a נערה
Na'arah because she’s able to marry herself. I mean, the תורה Torah
already says נערה, Na'arah, but the repetition presumably says only a נערה.
Na'arah. אוקיי, Okay, now the verse actually when it says נערה Na'arah
by the case of rape, writes it without the letter ה, hei,
אוקיי? okay? And therefore, the writing without the letter ה hei indicates
for the חכמים Chachamim that she’s not—even when she’s not a full
נערה, Na'arah, even when she’s a קטנה. Ketana. אוקיי, Okay, is it
what obvious? Oh, it’s that you're being facetious? I don't know, it’s
an interesting point that it’s not written with a ה. hei. I
mean, we could just put it down to spelling differences, but the
גמרא Gemara wants to learn everything from every hint. So the lack
of the ה hei says she’s not a full נערה. Na'arah. אפילו
קטנה במשמע. Afilu ketana b’mashma. שמע רב פפא בריה דרב חנן מבי
כלוחית. Shma Rav Pappa breih d'Rav Chanan m'bei Kluchis. So this Rav
Pappa heard this, ואזל אמרה קמיה דרב שימי בר אשי. v'azal amrah
kamei d'Rav Shimi bar Ashi. And he told this דרשה drasha to
Rav Shimi bar Ashi, that without the ה hei it implies even
a קטנה. Ketana. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him: אתון
אהא מתניתו לה. atun aha matnitu lah. You teach that idea that
without the ה hei it implies a קטנה Ketana on this discussion
about the קנס. knas. אנן אהא מתנינא לה. Anan aha matnina lah.
We teach it on the following discussion. אמר ריש לקיש: Amar Reish
Lakish: המוציא שם רע אקטנה. Hamotzi shem ra a-ketana. Says Reish Lakish,
there's another place the תורה Torah talks about special payments which we're
going to get to in the next פרק, perek, about a נערה,
Na'arah, about the man who claims that in the next morning all
about this issue about virginity and the נערה, Na'arah, the man who
claims the next morning that his wife wasn't a בתולה betulah and
that she had committed adultery, you know, that whole קרא kra about
מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra and then stoning her or he
has to pay a fine, etc. So would that apply to a
קטנה? Ketana? So Reish Lakish says no, that special פרשה parsha of
מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra applies only to a נערה, Na'arah,
even the חכמים Chachamim who say that the קנס, knas, the fifty,
applies to a קטנה, Ketana, would agree that the הלכות halachos of
מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra of the guy sort of spreading
ill report or whatever on his wife, that's only a נערה דוקא.
Na'arah davka. How do you know that? המוציא שם רע אקטנה פטור,
Hamotzi shem ra a-ketana patur, שנאמר, she-ne'emar, the verse says: ונתנו לאבי
הנערה, v’natnu l’avi ha-na’arah, pay to the father of the נערה. Na'arah.
נערה מלא דיבר הכתוב. Na'arah malei diber ha-katuv. There the word נערה
Na'arah is spelled full. It's spelled with the ה. hei. So that
implicitly tells you the reason the rabbis know that the case, our
case, of the קנס knas is even a קטנה Ketana is because
it's spelled without the ה, hei, whereas they don't always say נערה
Na'arah means קטנה. Ketana. In the case of מוציא שם רע motzi
shem ra where נערה Na'arah is spelled with the ה, hei, they
say it means only really a נערה. Na'arah. אוקיי, Okay, so that’s
actually a nice consistent דרשה.
drasha. So let’s see what the גמרא Gemara says. What though, that
in that whole פסוק, pasuk, in that
whole passage, that's the only time נערה... Na'arah... alright, but at least
it says the word נערה Na'arah and it's actually missing a ה.
hei. Fine, but at least it says it once. מתקיף לה רב
אדא בר אהבה. Matkif lah Rav Adda bar Ahava. Rav Adda bar
Ahava asks on this: טעמא דכתב רחמנא נערה. Ta'ama d'chtav Rachmana na'arah.
The reason you're saying the מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra it
is only a נערה, Na'arah, a real נערה, Na'arah, is because it's
with a ה. hei. הא לאו הכי הוה אמינא אפילו קטנה. Ha
lav hachi hava amina afilu ketana. Had it not been the extra
ה hei I would have said even if she's a minor? והא
כתיב: V’ha ktiv: ואם אמת היה הדבר הזה לא נמצאו בתולים לנערה.
v’im emet hayah ha-davar ha-zeh lo nimtze’u betulim la-na’arah. That if it
was true that she was not a virgin and therefore assumed to
have committed adultery, והוציאו את הנערה אל פתח בית אביה. v’hotzi’u et
ha-na’arah el petach beit aviha. They shall take the young girl out
to the father's house to the door of the father's house, וסקלוה,
u’skaluha, and stone her. So clearly if they're stoning the woman for
having committed adultery, she is an adult. If she were a minor
she would not be punished. וקטנה לאו בת עונשין היא, V’ketana lav
bat onshin hi, and a minor is not subject to punishment.
So he's not disagreeing with the הלכה.
halacha. You're right, מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra clearly the girl
is a נערה, Na'arah, not a קטנה, Ketana, because the תורה Torah
speaks about the possibility that if she committed adultery she'll be executed.
But you don't need the extra ה hei to tell you that.
You just know it from the fact that it's assuming that she's
an adult because it talks about her punishment if she committed adultery.
So the גמרא Gemara says: אוקיי, Okay, fine, אלא הכא, ela hacha,
you're right, we didn't learn it out from the ה. hei. We
learned out that מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra she was an
adult from the fact that the תורה Torah says that she would
be executed. But now that we know she's an adult in the
case of מוציא שם רע, motzi shem ra, now it can tell
us... how to read the significance of the presence or the absence
of the letter ה. He. So we don't start with this idea
that the letter ה He makes a difference, we start with the
idea that it's clear there it's an adult. And then we say,
ah, it's an adult! Oh, wait a minute! And here there's a
ה He and there there's not a ה. He.
Maybe that tells you whether the person is an adult or not.
אלא כאן נערה, Ella kahn na'arah, here we know it's an adult,
הא כל מקום שנאמר נער, ha kol makom shenee'mar naar, if it
didn't have the ה, He, we would say אפילו קטנה במשמע, afilu
ktana bemashma, even a minor, and that's how we know that by
the קנס, knas, according to the חכמים, Chachamim, it's even if she's
a קטנה. ktana. Okay, so that's something that we've already known, this
issue about the difference of רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir and the חכמים
Chachamim whether it applies to a קטנה.
ktana. Now we're finally up to today's דף, daf, top of מ"א
ע"א. mem aleph amud aleph.
Okay, now we get to these issues about בושת ופגם boshes upgam
that
we are, what do
you call it, that we've
established
that there's these different payments. There's the קנס knas
which is
a fixed
amount, which is
being called a קנס, knas, a fine, although we discussed yesterday that
it's really not so much of a fine as it's because the
father is not going to get
the מהר, mohar, the bride price he normally would have gotten, and
that's why he's getting this, right? And we discussed yesterday the whole
idea that the normal bride price of fifty שקל shekel was there
to protect the, you know, became a type of pseudo-כתובה kesubah and
was there to protect the woman's interest, and then it got later
moved to the back of the marriage, and also was there to
ensure that there was not overhasty divorce, and that was the whole
issue yesterday about whether there is a כתובה kesubah in the cases
of אונס ומפתה. ones umefateh. But anyway, so that from that perspective
you could have looked at the fifty as not so much of
a fine, but as compensating the father because he's not going to
get the bride price he normally would have gotten.
But the גמרא Gemara does not look at it that way. The
משנה, Mishna, the משנה Mishna looks at it as a fine,
as opposed to the payments for injury for בושת ופגם, boshes upgam,
those are payments of actual compensation of called ממון. mamon. Those are
monetary payments, not payments of, not fines. Why does that matter? For
the following reason. Let's look at our משנה, Mishna, what the different
הלכה halacha is between a monetary fine and monetary payment. So האומר
פיתיתי את בתו של פלוני, Ha'omer pitisi es bito shel ploni, somebody
says that I seduced this man's daughter, and therefore I'm liable for
all the payments. So משלם בושת ופגם על פי עצמו, meshalem boshes
upgam al pi atzmo, he pays for the embarrassment and the injury
based on his own testimony, ואין משלם קנס, ve'ein meshalem knas, but
he does not pay for a fine, and this is a principle
that fines can only be imposed by the court and only be
imposed, they don't exist, they're not like objective debts. They're, they're, like
it's a punishment imposed by the court, and it can only be
imposed if there's objective testimony, if there's external witnesses. Based on a
person's own testifying, he cannot obligate himself in a fine. It even
goes further than that, that sometimes the testifying even will exempt you
from a fine later on even if witnesses come and say you've
done it. But before we even worry about your admission exempting you,
certainly it does not obligate you. Okay, so if the person therefore
confesses, he only pays the monetary payments, the ones that are seen
as a type of compensation and not the ones that are seen
as a monetary punishment, the ones that are a fine. So משלם
בושת ופגם על פי עצמו ואין משלם קנס. meshalem boshes upgam al
pi atzmo ve'ein meshalem knas. האומר גנבתי, Ha'omer ganavti, and now we're
going to get off from the specific issue of קנס knas and
discuss other cases of קנס. knas. Somebody that says that I burgled,
ומשלם את הקרן על פי עצמו, umeshalem es hakeren al pi atzmo,
and he confesses it, he pays the principal based on his own
testimony, ואין משלם תשלומי כפל ותשלומי ארבעה וחמישה, ve'ein meshalem tashlumei khefel
vetashlumei arba'a vachamisha, but he does not pay the double and the
four and the five, because those are fines and that you don't
pay on your own testimony. המית שורי את פלוני, Hamis shori es
ploni, my ox gored a certain person, או שורו של פלוני, o
shoro shel ploni, or gored his ox, הרי זה משלם על פי
עצמו, harei ze meshalem al pi atzmo, then he pays, he pays
because those are compensation. Now the idea that there's compensation for killing
somebody, if your ox kills someone, that no, well we're not talking
about עבד, eved, that would be a fine, this is compensation, that's
a כופר, kofer, you know, a כופר kofer which is like a
ransom. So there is a question whether כופר kofer is seen as
to atone for my soul because it was my ox that gored
it and I'm basically therefore paying the value of myself, and therefore
it's not really a type of תשלומין, tashlumin, is it a קנס,
knas, how to understand it, that's one thing. But this משנה Mishna
presumably we understand that when an ox gored and killed somebody, you're
paying for the dead person and their value, and somehow again, use
the slave market and you give a dollar value to the person's
life. Okay, and therefore that's a type of תשלומין, tashlumin, not a
type of קנס. knas. So if you do that payment, or if
it gored another ox, you do it based on your own testimony.
But המית שורי עבדו של פלוני, hamis shori avdo shel ploni, if
my ox gored somebody's slave, then that's, now that we would say
is also a compensation for the lost slave. But here the משנה
Mishna makes a חידוש. chiddush. How do you know whether something is
a fine or a compensation? Okay, and it says if something is
a fixed amount and never changes based on circumstances, then it can't
be a compensation, because compensation always has to do with values and
circumstances. So if it's always fifty שקל... shekel... Thirty שקל *shekel* in
the case of the rape, or it's always thirty for the עבד
*eved*, then it's seen as a fine and not a compensation. We
could have just said we're going to fix the compensation at thirty
שקל *shekel*, but the משנה Mishnah *mishna* assumes not that way. Nope,
if it's a fixed amount, it's not a compensation, it's a fine.
אין משלמין על פי עצמו *ein meshalmim al pi atzmo*. זה הכלל
*zeh haklal*: so you don't pay when you testify, admit that your
ox gored somebody's slave. This is the rule: כל המשלם יתר על
מה שהזיק אינו משלם על פי עצמו *kol hamishalem yeter al mah
shehizik einu meshalem al pi atzmo*. If you're ever going to wind
up paying more than the actual damages, you don't do it based
on your own testimony. Now I want to say something because what
I actually said a minute ago, which is if it's fixed, it's
considered a fine, is not exactly what the משנה Mishnah, *mishna* says.
The משנה Mishna *mishna* says if you pay more, you could imagine
somebody that would, let's say, always pay less. Let's say for example,
we lived in a reality that all slaves were worth at least
fifty שקל *shekel*, fifty שקל *shekel* and up, and the תורה Torah
*torah* said you always pay thirty שקל *shekel*. So I might not
consider it a fine. I might just say that the תורה Torah.
*torah* puts a ceiling to your payment, right? The תורה Torah. *torah*
says you'll always pay a partial compensation. So if you sometimes pay
less than the damages, it doesn't prove that it's a fine. It
could just be saying you'll pay partial damages. But if there be
scenarios you pay more, if a certain slave was worth only ten
שקל *shekel* and you're going to pay thirty, so if the תורה
Torah *torah* will have you at times pay more, then clearly it's
a fine. Anything more than the actual damages. So since sometimes slaves
are worth less than thirty שקל *shekel*, and you will still pay
thirty שקל *shekel*, shows that we should look at this, the whole
thing here, as a קנס knas *knas*. Okay? Yes? Doesn't this set
up a situation where a person would want to admit to something?
Maybe they didn't do it? Yes. So in our משנה Mishna *mishna*,
you don't know that admitting actually gets you off the hook. You
just know that admitting to a קנס knas *knas* doesn't obligate you.
In theory, witnesses could come later and obligate you. It's a different
principle that when you admit to something, you actually get exempt even
if witnesses come later, and then there are some limits to when
we say that principle. Okay? But right, all our משנה Mishnah. *mishna*
said is that your own admission doesn't, doesn't obligate you. So there's
no incentive to admit according to our משנה *mishna*. Does it get
you off the hook of the additional? It didn't say that. Our
משנה *mishna* just says you don't obligate yourself based on your own
admission. It didn't say. Now you're right, there's another principle that, again,
there's a question about how much is it universal? The גמרא Gemara
*gemara* assumes it's universal, but it's not black and white, certainly in
these משניות *mishnayot*, that your admission gets you off the hook. It
just says your admission doesn't obligate you. All right? Doesn't obligate you
means sufficient in and of itself? Sufficient in itself, right, to obligate
you. But it is true that there's other הלכות *halachot* that your
admission actually can get you off the hook even if witnesses come
later. And when we get to that, we can discuss that, and
that is a surprising, right? Because then there's an incentive to admit.
But the, but the attitude of the גמרא Gemara *gemara* might be
sure, good, there's an incentive to admit because the purpose of this
is actually to get you to confess and whatever, maybe that's part
of the function it's supposed to serve. Looking at the English, I
was responding to the English that just says but does not pay
the fine. Well, it's true, does not pay based on the admission
itself. It doesn't, it doesn't tell you what would be the consequence
if there were. It means all we have is your admission. Your
admission is enough to make you pay one category, but not enough
others. מודה במקצת *modeh bamikzat*. Okay. All right, so let's keep on
going. וליתני *ulishni*? So our משנה *mishna* says, so why now we've
been talking about rape, rape, rape, why now do we switch to
the case of seduction? וליתני אנסתי *ulishni anasti*? Why doesn't it give
the case that a guy says I raped this woman and therefore
he pays the, the monetary payments but not the fine? לא מיבעיא
קאמר *lo mibaya ka'amar*: it goes without saying. לא מיבעיא אנסתי *lo
mibaya anasti*: certainly if he says he raped this woman, דלא קפגים
לה *delo kapagim lah*, he is not claiming that she's of ill
repute, right? He's the one that raped her. Again, you know, as
we know in ancient societies, if a woman was raped, it didn't
matter she was like she was the one that was shamed. But
the גמרא Gemara *gemara* is at least acknowledging that it doesn't mean
that she did anything wrong. So he's saying he's the one that
did this terrible act. So in that case, דמשלם בושת ופגם boshet
upgam, על פי עצמו *dumeshalem boshet upgam al pi atzmo*, so he's
going to pay it based on his own admission. אבל פיתיתי *aval
pititi*, but if he says that I seduced this woman, so basically
he's also saying something about her. He's, he's saying that she's loose,
that he's, he's spreading ill repute about her. דקפגים לה *dekapagim lah*,
so he's spreading ill repute about her. אימא לא eima lo, משלם
על פי עצמו *eima lo meshalem al pi atzmo*, so maybe we
won't let him pay. Right, it's an interesting point. He says I
seduced this woman and here I'm going to pay for the fine.
Maybe we should refuse to accept the money or allow him to
pay it because by allowing him to pay it, we are allowing
him to basically spread ill repute about this other woman, if he
says that she did this consensual act of sex with him. So
the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says, so in that case, אימא לא eima
lo, משלם על פי עצמו *eima lo meshalem al pi atzmo*, maybe
we don't let him pay. Maybe he's lying, maybe it's all part
of a whole scheme to make her look bad or something. Who
knows what it is? But we can't, you know, without objective testimony,
we maybe we shouldn't accept the money. קא משמע לן *kamashmalan* that
we do, that maybe we're able to bracket whatever reason he gave
and says he wants to pay the money, he'll pay the money.
Okay? And we don't have to be concerned about the explanation that
he gave for why he's paying it. מתניתין דלא כהאי תנא, Tanna
but it raises an interesting question, and now we're going to say
that there's actually a תנא Tanna. that disagrees. Our משנה is not
like the following תנא. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Beraita,
רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda
omer mishum Rabbi Shimon, אף בושת ופגם אינו משלם על פי עצמו.
af boshet upgam eino meshalem al pi atzmo. In the case of
seduction, he is not believed, and maybe even in the case of
rape, but certainly in the case of seduction, he is not believed
to pay even the payments of בושת ופגם, the monetary payments. He
pays nothing. If you have witnesses, he pays, but not based on
his own admission. לא כל הימנו שיפגום בתו של פלוני. Lo kol
heimenu she-yifgom bito shel ploni. We don't believe him that he is
to allow him to sort of spread ill repute about this man's
daughter. Therefore we don't accept. Now the interesting question is he saying
that only by seduction or, as again, in some Middle Eastern societies
even till today, even if a woman is raped, she's the one
who is shamed and she's the one who's an embarrassment and looks
bad. So maybe we wouldn't even accept his admission even in the
case of rape, because anytime a man says that whether he seduced
or raped a woman, the reality is that it winds up hurting
the woman. So maybe we shouldn't. But certainly in the case of
seduction, he says we don't accept his testimony even to make him
pay because that will just because that eventually will do more harm
to her than than if we accepted the money, than if we
didn't accept the money. Excuse me. So do we believe like if
bracketing aside, let's say okay, whatever the result, whatever the precipitating factors
of this encounter, let's say she gets injured otherwise through this? He
doesn't pay for that either? It's not because of an act. Like
he breaks her arm during this thing, it's a violent rape. Right?
They wouldn't have to pay anything? Yeah, I don't know. That's a
good question. How much do we package it all together? I don't
know. So could we separate it? We say we believe he broke
her arm, we don't believe anything else. Maybe. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, שיפגום בתו של פלוני. she-yifgom bito shel ploni. אמר
ליה רב פפא לאביי. Amar lei Rav Pappa l'Abaye. רב פפא Rav
Pappa says to אביי. Abaye. ניחא לה לדידה מאי? Nicha lah l'didah
mai? Let's say she says, no, whatever story he's telling me, I
want that money, and I think we should accept the money. Maybe
she doesn't admit she did it or not, but she says I'm
happy to have us take his money. So what do we say?
So the גמרא Gemara. says דילמא לא ניחא ליה לאבוה. Dilma lo
nicha lei l'avua. Okay, but maybe it's not the father isn't okay
with it. And maybe the father has a right not to be
embarrassed and so on. Part of these payments go to the father
anyway, or not part, the payments do go to the father. So
the גמרא Gemara says fine. ניחא ליה לאבוה מאי? Nicha lei l'avua
mai? Let's say the father says, I'll take some money. And she
says I'll take the money. So do we have to protect their
interest that they shouldn't be shamed by this according to this approach,
if they're not bothered by that? So the גמרא Gemara says דילמא
לא ניחא להו לבני משפחה. Dilma lo nicha lehu livnei mishpacha. No,
we do. Even though maybe the rest of the family will be
shamed as a result. So even though the rest of the family
isn't entitled to the money, maybe we as the בית דין Beis
Din have to sort of bring our sort of protect society and
protect the families and therefore we use that sort of policy considerations
to determine whether we should accept this testimony. It's quite interesting. Again
we've had other cases before where policy and הלכה halacha intersect. Right?
הלכתית, halachically, somebody admits to a fine, they're believed and they owe
the money. That's the הלכה halacha per se. If I admit that
I owe you a thousand dollars, then that's binding on me and
I have to court makes me pay a thousand dollars. But here,
in order to protect the interests of the family, even if the
immediate parties, the father and the daughter, are okay with it, maybe
we should refuse to accept your testimony. Let's see what it says.
So ליחלו לבני משפחה מאי? Lichlu livnei mishpacha mai? Let's say the
family, all the family says they're okay with it. No, אי אפשר
דליכא חד במדינת הים דלא ניחא ליה. ee efshar d'leka chad b'medinas
hayam d'lo nicha lei. Who knows? Maybe there's one family member in
China that would not want it. So therefore we have to protect
the interests of the family even where well, no, I mean the
payment might be אביה, aviha, but this is a different question. This
is a question about allowing somebody to spread ill repute and which
would be reinforced, which would be reinforced by maybe he's an idolater,
he's making the whole thing up. So do we allow somebody to
spread this rumor which will get reinforced by our accepting of the
money, or is it our jobs as sort of to protect society
and protect innocent people, to protect people that will indirectly be hurt
by this type of a claim? It's an interesting question. Of course
you could imagine other scenarios having nothing to do with rape, where
I admit to something which indirectly reinforces certain bad impressions of other
people and so on. How much do we allow these types of
policy considerations to interfere with the natural running of the court? Yes.
Seems like there are really witnesses to these things. If she says
he seduced me and he says yes I seduced her, we're not
going to accept that? Is that what we're saying? Just a second,
you mean what happens if she so meaning I think somebody raises
this question about what happens if she if she initiates the proceedings?
Like maybe this is a little bit different because she's the one
that came forth. If she's the one that actually initiated the proceedings.
actually says that it happened, not just is willing to take the
money, but says that it happened, right, then that might be a
different story. I'm trying to remember, I think תוספות Tosfos says something
about this. But she can't do the initiate. What if he initiates
and she says yes, you know what? Right, okay, so that's what
I said. Right. One minute. Let me read the context. No, acceptable
to take the money. Let's say they actually admit that it happened.
Right. Yeah, if you take a look at תוספות, Tosfos, he says,
there's a difference between saying okay we'll take the money. תוספות Tosfos
says two lines down in the תוספות Tosfos narrow lines, I mean
I won't get into the technical question he's asking, but he says,
היינו דמשום דקדם תבעו האב תחילה, Hainu d'mishum d'kodam teva'u ha-av techilla,
אין צריך לומר לאו כל הימנו. ein tzarich lomar lav kol heimeinu.
So תוספות Tosfos basically says when the father, maybe the daughter as
well, is the one that basically sues him and says you seduced
my daughter, you seduced me, you owe me this, then it's different.
Then basically they're themselves saying that it happened and they're the ones
putting it forth and therefore obviously then he would have to pay
even according to רבי שמעון's Rebbi Shimon approach here if he admitted
to it. So what happens if he said it and then they
afterwards admitted it happened, maybe that would be different also. Is there
any indication from the תורה Torah that this has to do with
the whole בני משפחה? bnei mishpacha? It seems that only people... Again,
Michael, we're not talking about the actual damage itself that the בני
משפחה bnei mishpacha are embarrassed. We're talking about, you know, we're talking
about that it didn't happen and we're just concerned about the claim
and how the claim reflects on them. It's not a payment in
the תורה. Torah It's our responsibility to protect society and protect innocent
people from having bad things said about them. It has nothing to
do with the payments in the תורה. Torah Okay? You said this
guy said bad things, it'll reflect poorly on the family. Do we
allow him to back that up through some type of collecting money
and hurt the reputation of the family? Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. האומר גנבתי משלם את הקרן. Ha-omer gannavti meshalem
es ha-keren. Now we get to a classic debate in the גמרא.
Gemara Let's see if we can at least get to the bottom
of the דף. daf. איתמר, Itmar, it was taught: פלגא נזקא. palga
nizka. When my ox gores another ox and it's a non-habitual gorer,
it's a תם, tam, it pays half damages. Okay, so here's an
interesting question: is the half damages a fine or is it partial
compensation? Is it קנס knas, or is it ממון? mamon? And notice
here, as I mentioned in the משנה, it's never more than the
damages, it's always less. So if it's always less, it's reasonable to
assume it's partial compensation, not a fine, even though it's not the
full amount. So what's the story? פלגא נזקא, palga nizka, half damages.
רב פפא אמר פלגא נזקא ממונא, Rav Pappa amar palga nizka mamona,
that is monetary, it's compensation, half compensation. ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע
אמר פלגא נזקא קנסא, v'Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua amar palga nizka
knasa, it's a fine. רב פפא אמר פלגא נזקא ממונא, Rav Pappa
amar palga nizka mamona, it's compensation. קסבר סתם שוורים לאו בחזקת שימור
קיימי, kasavar stam shevarim lav b'chezkas shimur kaimi, because he feels that
even untame oxen, even unhabitual oxen, cannot be assumed to naturally be
protected against going out and goring. Okay, you can't assume that they're
self-protected. You have responsibility to watch even your tame oxen. ובדין הוא,
uvadin hu, and therefore, if it goes and gores somebody, ובדין הוא
דמשלם כוליה, uvadin hu d'meshalem kulei, you really should pay full. רחמנא
הוא דחייס עליה, rachmana hu d'chayis alei, and but the תורה had
רחמנות rachmanus on you, דאכתי לא ועיד תוריה, d'achatti lo yaid toreih,
the ox hasn't been warned. So meaning you're negligent, but you're only
barely on this side of the line of negligence. And therefore the
תורה gives you a break the first three times. So basically, you
should be paying full compensation. You only pay half because the תורה
went easy on you. But clearly it's compensation, it's half compensation because
you're on this side of the negligence line. Okay?
Is there
any reason why the victim suffers by only getting half compensation for
their actual losses? Because they have the benefit of the same law.
Right, exactly. Okay. ובדין הוא, uvadin hu, yes, that's true, that there's
always a trade-off between the perpetrator and the victim. Okay. דאכתי לא
ועיד תוריה. d'achatti lo yaid toreih. ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע אמר
פלגא נזקא קנסא, v'Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua amar palga nizka knasa,
no it's a fine. קסבר סתם שוורים בחזקת שימור קיימי. kasavar stam
shevarim b'chezkas shimur kaimi. Before it's become habitual, you can assume that
your ox will be protected against going out and goring. You really
don't have a real responsibility to watch it. ובדין הוא דלא לשלם
כלל, uvadin hu d'lo leshalem klal, and therefore technically you shouldn't have
to pay at all. You were not negligent. You weren't negligent, so
what? Michael, you learn בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, if you're not negligent,
you're not liable. Okay, so you weren't negligent by not watching your
ox. רחמנא הוא דקנסיה, rachmana hu d'kensei, but the תורה fined you,
why? כי היכי דנינטריה לתוריה, ki heichi d'ninterei l'toreih, that you should
be more careful and watch your ox. Meaning the best way to
understand it is they're arguing about exactly which side of the line
of negligence you fall. Do you just fall over the line of
negligence or just under? So one approach is you just fall over
but you're barely negligent, so okay technically you should pay full, but
since you're barely negligent you pay half, but it's still compensation. The
other says you fall just under the line of negligence, so technically
you should be totally off the hook. But we really would like
you to be a little bit more careful, okay, and therefore we're
going to make you pay half even though you shouldn't be paying
anything to encourage you to be more careful. So that's the... And
the, at least the victim gets something, but not because we're claiming
you're negligent. Technically you're not negligent. So that's the question whether to
look at it as a fine or look at it as compensation.
Like a fine. Right. Well no, strict liability means with no negligence
you're חייב. chayav. When your animals go and gore, it's only due
to negligence. But the question is what do you deal with some
case that falls right on the line. You need negligence, what if
it falls right on the line and which side of the line,
and that's what's being debated.
Okay, so is the primary location of this debate here?
No, it also exists in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. Yeah, but here's
one of the locations. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
We'll skip the סימן, Siman, which is a way of knowing what
are the cases that're going to be looked at. תנן. Tnan. הניזק
והמזיק בתשלומין. Hanizak vehamazik batashlumin. We have a משנה in בבא קמא
Bava Kamma that says in a case of a שור תם, Shor
Tam, the both the damagee and the damager share the cost of
the damages, right? Because you split the cost because you only pay
half. בשלמא למאן דאמר פלגא נזקא ממונא, Bishlama leman damar palga nizka
mamona, if you say half damages is compensation, היינו דשייך ניזק בתשלומין.
hainu deshaich nizak batashlumin. That's what it means that the damagee pays
for half, because he should be getting full compensation but he had
to pay as it were for half. He only gets half when
he should be getting full. אלא למאן דאמר פלגא נזקא קנסא, Ela
leman damar palga nizka knasa, but if it's a fine, השתא דלאו
דידיה קשקל, hashta delav dideh kashakal, the half that the damagee is
getting, he doesn't really deserve because the damager wasn't negligent. So he's
already getting money he doesn't deserve. ובתשלומין איתא, Uvatashlumin isa, so what
does it mean to say that he shares in the cost of
the loss? Meaning in anything he's getting money. Now of course you
could say at the end of the day his ox is dead,
okay, but nevertheless
he's out an animal.
But he should be out the whole animal, okay, so in principle
he's not entitled to anything and he's getting half. How can you
frame that as he's sharing in the cost? Because if anything he's
lucky to be getting half. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
לא נצרכא אלא לפחת נבילה. lo nitzrecha ela lefchat neveila. No, this
is taught for the הלכה halacha of the deprecation of the value
of the carcass of the animal. Depreciation, thank you. Deprecation means something
else. פחת נבילה, pchat neveila, so meaning that if the carcass devalues,
you pay half of the cost of the difference between the live
animal and the dead one and then the damagee, the ניזק, nizak,
takes the carcass and if it appreciates over the next few days
and weeks or whatever, he suffers the full loss of that depreciation.
Okay, so therefore that's what it says that he's included in the
loss because he's going to suffer the full loss of the depreciation
of the carcass and that won't have to be paid by the
owner of the ox. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara. says פחת נבילה
תנינא. pchat neveila tnina.
We already talked about that. תשלומין נזק. Tashlumin nezek. The משנה says
that you pay the payments of נזק nezek and somehow from that
strange articulation we learn the principle מלמד שבעלים מטפלין בנבילה melamed shebaalim
metaplin biveila
that the owners actually have to deal with the carcass and if
it depreciates it's their loss. גמרא Gemara says חדא בתם וחדא במועד
וצריכא. chada btam vechada bmuad uztrizcha. No, it tells you twice, once
by a habitual gorer that the owners of the dead animal deal
with the carcass and once by a non-habitual and you need both.
ואשמעינן תם, Viyashminan tam, if you said תם tam משום דאכתי לא
יעד, mishum deachti lo yaid, so the guy's ox is not habitual
so he should not have to pay as much, so you the
owner have to deal with the depreciation of the carcass. אבל מועד
דאועיד, Aval muad deoeid, but the מועד muad where he was warned,
אימא לא, maybe the owner of the gorer should partly share in
the depreciation. ואשמעינן מועד, Viyashminan muad, had you told me about the
case of מועד muad משום דקא משלם כולו, mishum deka mshaleim kulo,
he's already paying the full amount so he shouldn't have to also
pay for the
depreciation. אבל תם, Aval tam, but I might say by the non-habitual,
אימא לא, since he's only paying half maybe also has to share
in the depreciation. צריכא, Tzricha, so it tells you in neither case
he shares. Fine. Anyway bottom line is is that the language that
they both share in the cost seems to reflect the idea that
it is partial compensation but the גמרא Gemara gets out of it.
Let's do one other case, turn the page at least. תא שמע,
Ta shma, come in here. מה בין תם למועד, Ma bein tam
lemuad, what's the difference between a habitual and non-habitual? שהתם משלם חצי
נזק, Shehatam mshaleim chatzi nezek,
the תם tam pays half damages, מגופו, migufo, and it also comes
out of the body of the gorer itself. You will never have
to pay more than the cost of the goring animal. Okay, so
if my right if my $100 ox gores your $1000 ox, okay,
I'm not going to pay you $500, I'm going to give you
my $100 ox and I'm going to be done with it. There's
even a question about how much you actually become an immediate owner
in my ox, okay, but the payments can only be collected from
the animal of the gorer itself. ומועד, Umuad, but the case of
a habitual gorer משלם נזק שלם, mshaleim nezek shalem, it's full damages
מן העליה, min ha'aliya, from the best of the property with no
limit. ולא, Vilo, okay, so those are the differences. ולא קתני, Vilo
katani, and it doesn't give as a difference שהתם אינו משלם על
פי עצמו, shehatam eino mshaleim al pi atzmo, that the תם tam
does not pay through self-admission, ומועד משלם על פי עצמו, umuad mshaleim
al pi atzmo, and the מועד muad does. So again that would
seem to indicate that they're both... They're both money. They're both compensation,
right? Because if one was a fine, there are other differences that
need to be pointed out. So this is another evidence that it's
תשלומים tashlumim and not a fine. Is that clear? Because if it
was a fine, we have the differences of our משנה. But says
תנא ושייר. Tanna v'shayer. No, there either is that difference about fine
and תשלומים, tashlumim, but it's not a complete list, it's an abbreviated
list. So גמרא Gemara says מאי שייר דהאי שייר? mai shayer de-hai
shayer? You don't just leave one thing off the list. So if
it's not a full list, what else was not on the list?
שייר חצי כופר. Shayer chatzi kofer. It left off half of כופר.
kofer. If an ox gores, a habitual, a non-habitual ox gores a
person and kills the person, do you when it's habitual, you pay
כופר. kofer. You pay the full amount. When it's non-habitual, you pay
חצי כופר chatzi kofer of killing a person or not? So that's
debated in the גמרא. Okay, so the גמרא says that also would
be was left off, that should also have been put there as
a difference and it wasn't, so it's not a complete list of
differences. Okay.
One minute.
No, so the point being, by the way, let me be clear,
that when it says חצי כופר chatzi kofer is a difference, it
doesn't mean that the מועד muad pays full כופר kofer and the
תם tam pays חצי כופר. chatzi kofer. That would be the exact
difference it said of full and half. The הלכה halakha actually is
that a תם tam doesn't pay anything if it kills somebody. It
doesn't pay חצי כופר. chatzi kofer. So whereas the מועד muad pays
full, the תם tam pays zero if it kills another person. So
let's just read one more line. Meaning to the difference is that
there's no חצי כופר. chatzi kofer. That normally the תם tam pays
half, here's another difference though that wasn't in this list, that when
it comes to כופר, kofer, killing a person, the תם tam actually
pays zero. גמרא says no, אי משום חצי כופר לאו שיורה הוא.
i mishum chatzi kofer lav shiurei hu. By the way, that's not
necessarily a difference because הא מני רבי יוסי הגלילי היא דאמר תם
משלם חצי כופר. ha mani Rabbi Yose HaGelili hi de-amar tam meshalem
chatzi kofer. There's an opinion that a תם tam does pay חצי
כופר. chatzi kofer. So it's not necessarily a difference. Anyway, once again,
we've got the idea of a list that says differences between תם
tam and מועד, muad, it does not mention the קנס idea, another
indication that the תם tam payment is money and not קנס, and
the גמרא finds a way to say it's not a complete list
and gets out of this.
Okay. לאו שיורה הוא מידי, lav shiurei hu midei, it wasn't left
off?
Yeah, it means that from the other side of the opinion, you
don't have to prove that something was left off because you can
argue that from the position of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose it wasn't
left off. Okay. So, you know what, alright, it's already 8:35. So
unfortunately we're going to have to end here and still be an
עמוד amud behind. Okay. Unless people want to stay another 10 minutes
and finish out to the end of the פרק. perek. Is anybody
prepared to do that or people want to go to דאווענען? davenen?
Fine. Alright, we will pick up tomorrow. No questions tomorrow.
I mean I'm okay if you want to go 10 minutes later
tomorrow if you're...
Why tomorrow any better than today?
At least I would
have דאווענט. davened.